Guide to the James A. Healy Collection of Irish literature, 1870-1976
Department of Special Collections
- Yeats, William Butler
  - The Wind Among the Reeds. London: Elkin Mathews. 1899., 3481
    I am very pleased to know that this book kept by me for just over 40 years, now goes to my brothers very good friend James. A. Healy. We were living in 3. Blenheim Road. Bedford Park Chiswick London W. <when> in 1899. Lily Yeats
    Healy penciled the date 10/15/38 beside each of the three inscriptions above.
    Inscription on second flyleaf: Lily Yeats April 21st 1899 London.
    Half title page: Watercolor, signed J.V..
    p. 1: Watercolor, covering entire page, signed: I.C.V. '04.
    p. 3: Watercolor, with large initial `0' (for the beginning of the first line of the poem, `0 SWEET everlasting Voices be still;') just over title of poem.
    p. 9: Watercolor, along entire outer side of page, signed AE.
    p. 15: Watercolor, covering entire page, signed Elizabeth C. Yeats.
    p. 17: Watercolor, on top of page, signed.
    p. 32: Watercolor, on top of page extending down outer side of page, signed.
    p. 34: Watercolor on lower half of page, signed 24 Aug. 1903..
    p. 51: Drawing in black ink on top of page, signed Jack B. Yeats.
    p. 53: Watercolor, covering entire page, signed A E..
    p. 56: Watercolor, extending over three quarters of page, signed NR.
    Loose sheet of stationery with printed address Coole Park, Gort, Co. Galway. Under address unfinished pen and ink drawing. On opposite page, inscription (in Lily Yeats' hand):
    By Robert Gregory
    Lady Gregory's son
    killed in the war -
    To illustrate old men
    admiring themselves in the
    water - In collected edition
    Inscription on loose sheets of paper (in Lily Yeats' hand except for the penciled dates, in Healy's hand):
    - Sheet #1:, 9/6/38 (pencil)
      Flyleaf - Little water colour of reeds in a lake - evening sky - by John Varley - who was married to my mother's sister Isabella Pollexfen - he was grandson of John Varley the watercolour painter the friend of William Blake - he himself was a good artist painted in Egypt, India, Spain etc - Aunt Isabella died June 1938 aged 89 -
      - Page 1. Poem The Hosting of the Sidhe decoration on margin by Ida Varley - daughter of above John Varley
      - Page 3. The everlasting Voices initial letter - by Elizabeth Corbet Yeats
      - Page 9 - The Host of the Air decoration two figures in margin by AE.
      - Page 15 - The Song of wandering Aengus decoration round margin by Elizabeth C. Yeats
    - Sheet #2:, 9/6/38/ (pencil)
      - Page 17 The Song of the old Mother decoration figure of old woman by Pamela Coleman Smith
      - Page 32. The Cap & bells decoration figures by Mary Cottenham Yeats - (Mrs. Jack. B Yeats)
      - Page 51 Hanrahan laments because of his wanderings black & white drawing at top of page by Jack B. Yeats
      - 53 The travail of passions decoration of figures by AE
      - page 56 Hanrahan speaks to the lovers of his songs in coming days decoration of figures by Nora Murray Robertson - a famous painter [who has] one [painting] in the Municipal gallery Dublin
      - Loose sheet of notepaper. Printed address. Coole Park Cort - C Galway - pen & ink sketch unfinished by Robert Gregory - Lady Gregorys son killed in the war -
        all paintings are signed -
    - Sheet #3:, 12/4/38 12/13/38 (in pencil)
      P.S. I cannot say for certain whether the poems in the Wind Among the Reeds were all written for love of a lady - I think some were written to Maud Gonne - but of course I do not really know - L - Y
      Inscriptions on three sheets in an envelope which is annotated:
      For Lily Yeats' copy of her brother's Wind Among the Reeds, which AE, Jack B. Yeats, Mrs. Mary Cottenham Yeats, Elizabeth Yeats, Pamela Coleman Smith, Nora Murray Robertson, and others, have illustrated.
      On back of envelope: Recd by JAH 1/3/39 (pencil)
    - Sheet #1:
      310 Riverside Drive
      Apt. 516
      New York
      January 1st 1939
      Dear Jim -
      Here is the inset I promised you for your copy of The Wind Among the Reeds. I hope it conforms to what you want. If it doesn't, I will rewrite it for you.
      With every sincere wish to you and your family for the New Year,
      I am
      Joseph Campbell
    - Sheet #2:
      THE WIND AMONG THE REEDS: W.B. Yeats: 1899
      This is a lovely book, and it has been a joy to look at its embellishments; most often by writers and artists I have known.
      One of the loveliest lyrics in it - indeed, one of the most perfect of its time from the point of view of literary technique - is `The Cloths of Heaven'.
      Had I the heavens' embroidered cloths, Enwrought with golden and silver light, The blue and the dim and the dark cloths Of night and light and the half light, I would spread the cloths under your feet: But I, being poor, have only my dreams; I have spread my dreams under your feet; Tread softly because you tread on my dreams. Out of a deep personal emotion it springs; but like all work of its kind, through a subtle alchemy that only the poet knows, it becomes the impersonal utterance of every lover that loves hotly.
    - Sheet #3:
      Who was the woman who inspired this lyric, and others, in The Wind Among the Reeds?
      She is still happily living, old now in years but ever-young in spirit - one whose early ideals have not been surrendered to the violence or the chicanery of Irish life; a worshipper before the shrine of traditional Irish beauty; a friend of the Irish poor and outcast; a comforter of the soldiers and prisoners who served Ireland through direst suffering from the latter days of Humanism to the Civil War of 1922-23. Her activity, I believe, can only end with her death; but for such a character there is no dissolution.
      Poetical exile, I hail her - Maud Gonne!
      January 1st, 1939
      Another copy of Lily Yeats' bookplate laid in.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Words for Music Perhaps and Other Poems. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1932., 3371
    One of 450 copies. E.C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
    For James A Healy The Poems about Lady Gregory those on pages 8 & 9 are the best in the book. Lady Gregory died I think in 1932. At the request of her family I stayed during the last year of her life at Coole Park. I was not not [ sic] there when she died. I had gone to Dublin, sent by her I think to ask some questions of her
    surgeon. I got a telegram that she was sinking but it was delayed [and] I arrived too late. After the telegram had been sent to me she got up, dressed, & sat in her study with an open book. The parson called went up & came away `I think I cheered her up. I will come again next week' He had not noticed anything. He had no doubt gossiped a little. She would not have let him speak of religion that was her souls secret W B Yeats 1938
    W B Yeats May 1933
- Yeats, William Butler
  - The Words upon the Window Pane. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1934., 3375
    One of 350 copies. Elizabeth C. Yeats' bookplate laid in. Inscribed by author on front flyleaf:
    For my friend James A Healy I wrote this play as a help to bring back a part of the Irish mind which we have been thrusting out as it were foreign. Now that our period of violent protest is over we claim the Anglo-Irish eighteenth century as our own. W B Yeats
    Inscribed on last back flyleaf, upside down:
    `An aimless joy is a pure joy' - W B Yeats
- [Yeats, William Butler]
  - Images of a Poet. Exhibition catalogue. 1961.